[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it e
software magazine online at
[Music]
computer.org/software. For software
engineering radio, this is Robert
Blumen. Today I'm joined by Tyler Flint.
Tyler is the CEO of Qpoint, a firm that
focuses on egress observability. Prior
to point, he was the co-founder of three
other PA companies and was a software
engineer at Digital Ocean. Tyler,
welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you. I really appreciate you
having me on, Robert. It's great to be
here. Happy to have you. Is there
anything else about your background
you'd like to cover? I don't know that
my background is all that important
other than just it feels like I've been
in this space for so long that I'd
watched the cloud grow up. And I do have
a funny story about containers in the
Linux kernel before they were a thing.
But if it presents itself, I'm happy to
tell that story. Well, we're all about
staying on topic here. So, I'm going to
pass on that and get right to the main
topic of our conversation, which is
managing external API dependencies.
Before we talk about managing external
services, can you situate the problem?
What type of systems or architecture are
we talking about that have external
dependencies? Yeah, that is a great
question. So most applications today
have at least one sort of external
dependency. Most have dozens or hundreds
or even thousands. And so dependencies
can take the form of either internal
service dependencies like a microser
type of application or really any
application that has a vendor or third
party API dependency. And so almost
every company that exists today has at
least one dependency on billing API or
some sort of management API that they
depend on for critical functionality.
Give some other examples beyond the one.
Yeah. So there's kind of two domains.
One domain is this micros service
architecture that we've seen proliferate
in the last you know 15 years. And to a
particular service in a microser app
everything is a dependency. Every
external service is an external
dependency. And in a large organization
usually those services are run by
isolated teams that pretty much act in a
way as if they're an external vendor.
And so when we look at the actual vendor
or third party dependencies, there's a
lot of dependencies that are spread
across billing APIs. There's a lot of
APIs across customer relationship
management APIs, a lot of automation
tooling or text, phone, other audio
platforms. There's a lot of dependencies
lately on external LLMs like OpenAI or
Anthropic. And so what we have seen is
that modern applications are really a
sprawl of these service dependencies.
You know large enterprise that's
operating a micros service architecture.
You said just now that if I work on a
team that implements service A, we're
responsible for that. Service B may
appear to us to be external, but surely
there are differences between that and a
service that we buy from another
organization entirely where no one there
works for the same boss at any level.
Yeah, absolutely. The levels of
accountability are different and the
lines of communication are certainly
different. So probably the biggest
difference that you see is if you have
an external vendor third party
dependency then while yes you have a
contract and you're trying to hold them
accountable to the terms that they have
presented to you it is incumbent upon
the team to ensure that the application
is resilient to the uptime and
performance of that third party vendor
because at the end of the day while you
can go make some noise and you can try
to influence their internal operation
you really have to accept the uptime and
reliability of that vendor. Whereas an
internal service, you can go get that
other team in a meeting and you can say,
"Hey, your SLA does not meet our SLO. We
have to figure out how to compromise
here or else we're going to have some
difficulty." So there is a fundamental
difference with vendors, not so much.
And you just kind of really have to be
resilient. Thank you for that. Another
distinction I wanted to go into is are
external services necessarily paid or
are there a lot of free services in the
mix? Yeah, there are a lot of free
services. Well, and then there's also
with free tiers something might be free
to your team and you're going to get one
level of service and then when you start
paying you get a different level of
service. But there are a lot of free
APIs but more particularly free tier
usage. I want to now start talking about
what the footprint of these services is.
You said the number of external services
an organization have it could be as few
as one but range up into the thousands.
That was one of my questions. Are these
services accessed from data center from
public cloud VPC or where is the origin
of the access? Yeah. So in particular
there are two different segments within
an organization. There's corporate IT
where you're really trying to limit the
employees and what they have access to
which is really not the segment. That's
an entire industry a growing industry
sassy that has a lot of phenomenal
products. And then where we are focusing
our effort is production services.
Production services that you're running
within your data centers that are
reaching out across boundaries across
public networks. And so the connections
that are originating are primarily from
the various apps that have been written
or workflows. So it's really anything
that is running on a server that starts
to make a connection out. And so we can
classify them in a lot of different
ways, but primarily they're from
applications that are running on your
infrastructure. They're from scripts or
tasks that run on the infrastructure.
What we're seeing a lot of now is a lot
of agents, AI agents that are starting
to talk externally. And then also, which
is really concerning to organizations,
is a user that has maybe shell access
that is running programs that is
reaching out. So there's a lot of
different sources of the connections,
but primarily where we're focused is
anything that's running within your
protected environment. Your production
infrastructure where you also have your
most precious resources, databases
containing company secrets, propriety,
and anything that has access to those
really needs to be considered from both
the security perspective, but also
performance and reliability or your
reputation. I expect most organizations
have some kind of gating to adopt a new
service. Two things I can think of. One
would be whitelisting the IP for egress
out of the controlled networks and
another is someone has to agree they're
going to write a check or authorize
payment if you're having a paid service.
Could you elaborate on what is the
adoption process? What are the gates and
steps in that? Yeah. Well, unfortunately
for us, what we have found is it is very
different across organizations. There
are some organizations who adopt a
policy which is we're not going to allow
anything to talk out and if you want to
create a new contract or use a new
service, the very first conversation has
to start at the door of security and
that's the first step in procurement.
There are other organizations who are a
little bit more open to bringing it in
to incubate pilot something leave
security out of it and as long as
there's some sort of handshake we can go
ahead and pilot this thing and we're
talking now to their external APIs and
then down the road we'll figure out how
to incorporate that in and then there's
all sorts of variations in between. So,
you know, without naming names, there's
I can tell you there are three prominent
companies that these are three common
household names. And one of them
essentially won't allow a new vendor
into their organization unless they're
willing to spend multiple thousands of
dollars just to start the security
auditing process, which certainly keeps
a lot of vendors out. There's another
company that has a process whereby they
have to have a contract in place and
they check daily to make sure that that
contract is still valid and they will
literally enforce or gate their
connections based on the validity of
that contract. And then another
organization and I just use this for
contrast and of course I can't name the
names here but they were acquired. It
was very public acquisition and part of
the acquisition is you have to have a
bill of materials all of your external
vendors and when they went through that
audit they had hundreds of vendor usages
that nobody knew where it started where
they came about there was no paper trail
and so it's just it's kind of all over
the place and I think it just depends on
the operational processes. You raised an
interesting point there where I was
expecting to hear about companies having
a lot more services than what they knew
about because of adoption. But a general
thing I've seen in security is we're
really good at having lots of
justifications for why I need to add
Tyler to this group. I need to give
Tyler all the credentials. I need to
give Tyler roles and permissions. Much
less good at Tyler's job
responsibilities have changed. He's left
the company. We need to make sure all
this stuff is revoked. Do you see that
asymmetry in the management of vendors
as well? Oh, everywhere. And one of the
first ways that that is exposed is
through API tokens. So, as we started to
talk to companies, one of the very first
things that they brought up was, can you
create an inventory of the API tokens
that are being used? And that way we can
come in and find out if those are the
tokens that are supposed to be used or
how long have they been used, how long
have they been in rotation. And what we
found that was quite surprising to me
was that these are sophisticated teams
with operational excellence using
secrets management software. And even
then there's a lot of questions as to
where all of those tokens are being
used. When was that token created? Who
was it created for? Is there some sort
of expiration that's looming? If that
token starts getting rejected, do we
know why that token is getting rejected?
And that really speaks to what you were
just inquiring, which is often times a
service and an integration is set up.
And then the care and proper feeding of
that integration is if it works, it
works. Don't fix it if it's not broke.
And and then that leads to some
governance concerns later down the road.
I have a question which you've answered
but I'm going to put it out there anyway
which is do organizations tend to have a
good understanding their dependencies
answer no. What I'm going to ask you is
tell a story about something that you
happen either happened to a company
because of an unknown dependency or a
surprise during an audit. Actually it's
so common. So, I I have plenty of these
stories, but it's so common that what we
actually found is that we're able to
build it as part of our onboarding
workflow that when you install the
agent, the first thing we do is we bring
you into your inventory and then we just
wait for the surprise. We wait for you
to realize, hey, what is that or why are
we using that or where is that coming
from? And so far in every instance where
we've run any sort of pilot or even an
onboarding experience, they're really
surprised. So they're either surprised
in that they're using a vendor that they
didn't think they were using or I'll
tell you the first one that comes to
mind is that there's a popular feature
flagging application that you know a lot
of companies use and the team was
certain that they had no critical
dependencies on it. they were certain
that it wasn't calling into that API on
every single request. And so they put
this in and it immediately popped to the
top as their highest consumed vendor.
And when they looked at that, they
realized that there was a direct
correlation between their own website
traffic and then how much traffic they
were sending out to that vendor. And it
occurred to them that they had a problem
with the way that their application was
implemented and it was asking on every
single request and there was no caching
in between and there was no no fallback.
And so that's just a recent one that
comes to my mind. But the other more
common one is that as soon as they turn
it on, they immediately realize how many
monitoring tools and solutions that
they're using. And often times the
question is, wait, I thought we turned
that off and it's still running. You
know, it's still running somewhere. So,
it's really fun. Actually, it's been
really fun to kind of experience those.
Now, you're doing a great job at
answering questions before I ask them. I
wanted to ask about risk factors. What
risk do external service providers
create? You've answered that a bit in
your last answer, but could you
elaborate in anything you haven't
already covered? There are three main
areas that we approach. So, one of them
is cost. There's a big risk to cost
through attribution and the most common
thing there and we see it on social
media where somebody suddenly gets a
bill that is a little bit more than they
were expecting and then the question
becomes who's responsible for that which
service which application which process
where is this coming from and so we
bucket that into the cost and
attribution and the one last thing I'll
say on that category is especially for
companies that make API calls on behalf
of their customers. There is a big
question of cost and attribution. If
their bill comes back from a vendor that
is directly proportionate to the amount
of usage from one of their customers,
they need better tools to understand the
risk of cost. So that's one. The other
is compliance and risk from a security
perspective. So exposure there's a
handful of questions in that that we
hear all the time which is especially
from CISOs from VP of security. What
they want to know is who are we talking
to outside of this organization? Which
applications or services are connecting
to them? Where in the world are these
connections terminating into what data
are we exfiltrating? Do we know what
types of data are being exfiltrated? And
so we've really focused on trying to
provide some of that understanding so
they can ask those questions. We do that
through an inventory and governance. We
show them the vendors. We show that all
of the applications, track that back,
where it's coming from, where in the
world it's going, and we have a map of
where all your connections are going to.
And then also we show on the services
that you would like, we can add some
sensitive data scanning to extract the
types of data. And then the third
category is really about reputation. And
this is really the performance and
reliability aspect. And one of the
things that we're learning a lot about
is maybe perhaps I had the wrong
perspective when I got into this
initially thinking that it was going to
be so important for teams to be able to
hold their vendors accountable. And
certainly there's an aspect of that. But
what we are hearing is that the burden
of resilience is falling on these teams
and they're much more concerned about
ensuring that their applications are
resilient to the things they cannot
control. So, as an example, very
well-known company that happens to
operate software on cruise lines runs
into challenges where their network is
unstable many times throughout the
journey. And they spend a lot of time
trying to figure out if their software
is reliable, is it accountable? And they
spin up environments specific to test
network latency, packet loss. And so one
of the things that they're working with
us on is a way to use our technology to
simulate all of these conditions without
having to spin up and provision all of
this expensive infrastructure and just
be able to modulate those things
directly in the kernel through EVPF.
Sorry, that's probably a lot more than
your original question, but the three
main areas are cost, compliance, and
exposure. And then the third is
reputation through performance and
reliability. Those are all good areas. I
want to drill down a little bit into
cost. One question I had is are there
situations where yeah, we know about
that service. We agreed to pay for it.
We want it, but we're using 10 times
more of it than what we thought and we
didn't know. Yes. So, we have seen that
scenario in three variations. So the one
is exactly what you're saying, which is,
wow, we're using this a lot more than we
thought, and we didn't realize that we
were using it so much. Now we see how
much we're using it. We can dive in to
see if there's ways to cut that. And in
that scenario, one of the first
questions that they have is, could we
implement some sort of squid proxy
somewhere and do some caching so that we
can minimize the amount of API calls
that we're doing on that vendor. So
that's one. The other one is the
scenario where they're not monitoring
their usage and then suddenly the vendor
says no more. You're getting rate
limited and what they will experience
immediately is a massive service
disruption. And then suddenly turns into
this wild goose chase. Why are all these
services offline? And they have to go
look in their mountain of logs to figure
out what's happening. And then they're
looking down for everyone or just me.
This vendor says they're online. And
then when they look into it, they
realize, oh, we've been rate limited.
Wait, why are we rate limited? Who
knows? Why are we using this more than
our limits? Does anybody know what we've
been doing recently? And so that's the
second case of being able to figure that
out. And then the third is, you know,
one of the most elusive of those. I
alluded to this briefly, was when you're
making API calls on behalf of your
customers, then it gets really complex
like our usage of this vendor. Are we
getting rate limited because one of our
customers is using 90% of our quota or
are we evenly distributed? Do we need to
scale up or do we just need to throttle
this one customer? And those are the
types of questions that are really
challenging for organizations to answer
and just really expensive when those
scenarios arise. You talked about
caching and monitoring which I want to
come back to. There's an area I want to
explore a bit more about. If you have an
essential service and you can no longer
use it, then are you out of business and
what does incident response look like
when that happens? Well, we were just
having a conversation around this
yesterday with a company and they made
it very clear and this is usually what
we find. There are a handful of
dependencies that they would say are
absolutely missionritical and then there
are other dependencies that are
ancillary, auxiliary and they want to
approach the relationship very
differently. They want to put so much
effort into the dependencies where if it
goes offline they're in big troubles.
They literally told us yesterday that
was they have one dependency where if
they have even a single failed request,
they have to ensure that the retry of
that request has been triply persisted
in their batch or retry queue or else it
sends an alarm to the highest levels.
And that was really surprising to me to
hear that they spend so much time
ensuring that this one particular vendor
always always works and that they have a
backup plan. Whereas the other ones are
kind of more like, yeah, if they don't
work, it's good to know and maybe we can
shift left a little bit and know quicker
and save ourselves some time. But yeah,
on these handful of these, if something
is trending in a direction, we want to
know about it. I can think of one
example of a service like that would be
if you're selling something and you have
a payment processor. Then you can't said
payment your business stopped. Are there
other common examples of that one
critical service? So the one that
they're referring to yesterday was a
customer of record type service and for
this particular company relationships
and customer relationships is core to
their business and so they have to
ensure that anything that happens where
it crosses a line. We've heard this as
well in fintech when there's quite a few
phenomenal fintech companies that are
creating well not virtual banks but
where they're presenting a banking
experience that's backed by traditional
banks and when these experiences are use
virtual cards etc they need to be very
very certain that all of the API
requests that go back to the bank have
been registered and if they failed that
also needs to be registered. The example
you gave a minute ago, retrying failed
requests. That's one strategy for
ensuring that critical services are
resilient. What are some other
strategies for resilience of critical
services? Well, one strategy that I
thought was fascinating and kind of
going off of the fintech and this was
early on when we were just trying to
formulate a hypothesis around this. And
so there's a financial company that has
terminals in various salons and other
locations that take credit cards and
credit card payments. And they then
through a series of operations relay
that back to the bank API. And what they
ultimately found was that it was a lot
safer for them if they couldn't have
that API request go through to just
bubble all the way back up. This
transaction was not successful. Try
again. and they just weren't able to put
the resilience systems in place to be
able to get the guarantees. So for them,
you know, you can imagine how important
it is to understand when something is
failing, that means they're not taking
money and they're not going to retry
either until that's resolved. And so for
them knowing the very moment, you know,
a lot of times companies are looking
more for an error rate or if the error
rate hits a certain limit. And in this
case, the company was if a single
request fails, someone's getting paged.
And we need to make sure that we're
looking and making sure that was an
isolated instance as opposed to a trend
that's about to make a very bad day for
our financial team. In many verticals,
there are multiple competitors. What do
you think about having a backup vendor
or having two vendors and if one fails,
you've still got one? We've heard a lot
about that. I think one of the initial
ideas, we didn't end up going this way,
but one of the ideas that we heard a lot
from our network was creating a way to
have pluggable vendors for a specific
endpoint and kind of creating a uniform
API similar to kind of what happened in
the telecom space where the leader came
out with the API for text messages and
voice messages and then all these other
competitors just kind of adopted that
same API so they could reuse the same
client. And that was something that
we've heard. We haven't gone that route
but you know it may come back up in the
future. Going to switch tracks a bit.
Talk more about security. Starting with
how are external services authenticated?
So the number one universal approach is
going to be through some sort of API
token and then there are other layers
that can be added. So one of the other
common layers is to ensure that only
trusted clients are connecting is you
can have whitelisted IPs. Unfortunately
that is proving to be more and more
complex for organizations and for
vendors especially where a lot of
clients are now moving on cloud. they've
got containerized workloads, IPs are
changing and so in order to accomplish
that level of security, what they have
to do is they have to push everything
through a proxy or a subnet and then
they can whitelist a range of IPs. So
primarily that's the approach. So some
of the more larger companies are using
what they call either an egress gateway
or an egress access point. And what they
do in that case is they push the
accountability back onto the application
workloads to connect through this
dedicated location and then they'll use
something like MTLS and that way it has
to verify this is who you are before
we'll allow that to go out. So that's
currently the two main approaches for
authentication or the two layers that I
should say. One of the things that we're
particularly excited about is we've been
working with design partners to sort of
push this quite a bit. So if you think
about what's happened on the inbound in
the industry where for a long time there
were firewalls for inbound and there
still are firewalls. Well then there was
an explosion of web application
firewalls operating at all sorts of
different layers. Even up at the edge
now we see some really prominent
players. That's web application
firewalls. And what they're doing is
they're essentially letting the
connections go through and they're
observing what they're doing. And the
moment they can see something, they can
fingerprint, let's say a DDoS attack or
some sort of application specific attack
that they can detect right away, they
just close the connection. And what
we've been working on with our
technology, it would be the inverse of
that. We're calling it a client
application firewall. And so it runs in
the Linux kernel. It does essentially
the same thing. It starts to fingerprint
a lot of these things or it starts to
look at the connections and what they're
doing and allows companies to create
very granular sophisticated policies
that have context from say the process,
the containers, the deployments, the
environment variables as well as the
connection and the and the network
layer. And so with this approach, we're
able to bring a new layer of security to
these connections to allow a company to
do something like say, hey, let's make
sure that only the billing team has
access to our banking APIs. And they can
do that by creating a policy that says,
let's make sure that it's only workloads
that are part of the following
deployment or namespace. And then here
are the vendors. and we can detect if a
connection is attempted and it doesn't
belong to all of those, then we can kill
the connection directly in the Linux
kernel via ebpf. And there are all sorts
of really fascinating use cases that
we're starting to uncover that fall in
in that. And just one other I'll just
real quick is there's a one of the
largest companies in the world has a new
well I don't know if it's new but to me
it sounded new policy where they say
that if we're going to reach out to an
external vendor whatever that API token
is that API token cannot have been
provided to the application via an
environment variable because the
environment variables are visible to
anyone who can see the system or the
proc file system. So what we were able
to put together was a scenario where we
see one we can look at the connection
what's going across the wire. We can
look at the header the HTTP header and
see the token and if the value of that
token matches an environment variable on
that process we can kill that connection
and those are the types of things that
we're really excited to be able to dig
into through our technology. If I
understood the description of the
network traffic fingerprinting that
would fall broadly under the realm of
authorization because it limits who may
access a particular service. Did I
understand that correctly? Yeah. Yeah.
So, a lot of organizations right now are
are looking to the service mesh to be
able to solve these problems. And
sometimes that's great, but other times
it's not the right fit. and the times
where it's not the right fit. One of the
challenges is that service mesh creates
a lot of operational burden to the team
as well as the sidecar dependencies all
over. And then the other problem is that
especially with a lot of large
enterprise companies who have not yet
moved everything on to cloudnative type
workloads, they've got a lot of
heterogeneous workloads. The challenge
becomes how do we create an identity?
How do we enforce that identity? How do
we ensure that this thing can go here,
this thing can go there and it's a lot
of operational burden and there are
teams that do it and do it well and
we're learning from them. What we're
excited about is to pull the barrier
down quite a ways and so the barrier
would be well if you have a Linux kernel
that is capable of running eBPF then you
can run a rule set that will ensure that
the right things are going to the right
locations. I'm going to change
directions again. And I want to move on
talking about testing which is a big
topic. Start with developer is
integrating a new service. How do they
go about testing it in either their own
workstation or environments they have
access to? The really common way is
usually they'll go and get a test
account or some of the really good
vendors will provide sandbox accounts
that give them access to things maybe
virtual. And so they'll integrate that
in, they'll run it in their workflow and
verify that things are working the way
that they are. And then the primary
operational mode for 90 plus% of
organizations is okay, it works. Let's
go ahead and ship it. And then all of
the challenges begin at that point. Once
it begins, then they start to realize,
well, how do we run end to-end tests in
our in our CI system? And if we do run
these end to-end tests in our CI system,
how can we ensure that only the
locations that we intended to use are
being accessed? And so one of the
challenges that teams face is the hidden
cost of transient dependencies. And
there are certain application ecosystems
that are more wellknown for this. Not to
pick on anyone here, just there are some
that are very well known uh for having
transient dependencies. And one of the
big surprises is that if you pull in a
dependency and it works locally, then
you go and run it in production and
maybe it's not running in production and
they start to they start to ask why and
come to find out that the dependency has
a dependency and that dependency calls
out for something and it can't get that
and for whatever reason, maybe the
firewall policy, maybe just doesn't
work, the network doesn't allow it and
now it's not working and they're
troubleshooting this dependency and
they're trying to figure out why what
what happened and all all to find out
that it was actually a dependency first
had a dependency on going and grabbing
something else first. So the idea is
that hopefully we can help shine a light
on some of those things. But right now
it definitely seems like the common
practice is developer gets it working
locally and ship it and then kind of
figure out how things work over time.
It's usually easier to get access to the
happy path. You can test that it works
when everything's good. Is it fair to
say that often the error codes and what
errors look like are less well
documented or they don't all appear in
the testing you can do in a sandbox.
Absolutely. And I'll even add one other
layer of pain. So the problem will arise
in that most organizations are not
recording all of the connections or
requests and it's very expensive
especially at a high scale. And so what
will end up happening is you'll have a
user who is continuously reporting over
and over to support, this isn't working.
Here's my screenshot. And the support
team will look at that screenshot and
they'll say, yeah, it looks like it's
not working. And then they'll go and
create a ticket. And then some project
manager will prioritize it. The
developer will look at that and they'll
say, well, how do I reproduce that? And
then they have to go back to the
customer. Well, I'm doing this. I'm
doing that. And then they go and they
try to reproduce it. And then so often
these things get just categorized as you
know cannot produce and then they'll
just sit there forever. And so one of
the things that we are really really
aware of is our ability to see the wire.
So we are on the wire and in fact that's
our core philosophy is that we are the
source of truth because we are on the
wire. We've tapped into the wire. We can
see all these interactions. And so with
our pluggable system, we can have rule
sets that look for errors or error
conditions or things that are outside of
the norm. And it's a lot more manageable
to record the exceptions and store
those. And so then what happens is these
teams and these security or sorry the
support teams when they pass it over the
wall, it can come with things like
customer ID. The developer can go and
match that up. Oh, here was the request
that went across the wire. Let me go and
and look at that payload that was sent.
Oh, that's why it's completely clear.
Then they can take that payload, they
can dump it into their system and see
the result, fix it, and they're on their
way. We've been talking about testing
our code, which consumes the services.
Should organizations adopt a posture of
testing the service as well, writing
test suites, load testing, error
testing, whatever they can think of.
That is really
fascinating. You know, I had not
considered that.
Yes, I I would tend to agree with you. I
think that's something that should be
considered. So, now that you're
considering this, could you think of
from your experience something that an
organization might find by doing this
kind of testing that they would only
otherwise learn the hard way? Yeah,
actually, one of the things that that
seems really obvious is that API
documentation tends to drift. And if you
build an integration and like you
mentioned, you've built an integration,
you're running through the happy path
and you look on the docs, okay, when
this scenario happens, then yeah,
everything looks good and we'll we'll
continue on our way. Then what ends up
happening is in production, you're going
to encounter that scenario and
unfortunately that vendor is not going
to be it's it's really hard to hold
vendors accountable. they are. If you're
fortunate enough to have vendors who
listen, maybe they're startups and
they're much more sensitive to things
not working correctly. But for the most
part, vendors are what they are. And I
can totally see what you're saying that
if you're able to write a client and
verify and run everything, then that
would essentially ensure that your app
has resilience. Okay, moving on to the
next big domino. You've mentioned a few
times either uh organizations don't know
how much of an API they're consuming or
you have some tooling in your product
that helps with that. Could you comment
generally on monitoring and
observability of external services
whether somebody is using your product
or not? How should they approach that?
Well, I'll tell you how they're
currently approached and the
differentiation for how how we look at
it. Currently, monitoring is primarily
integrated into applications via SDKs
and there are some agents and monitoring
solutions that will monitor the system
itself, but primarily monitoring is done
with with SDKs. And so what we tend to
find is that we'll come into an
organization and there may be a handful
of applications or teams that have done
a really thorough integration of a
particular SDK and have some pretty good
observability and others maybe not so
much. And so one of the reasons why and
I go back to this we go back to the
truth is on the wire and you know two
ways of thinking about it for us we
think about the truth is on the wire and
gold is in the stream. Essentially, it
kind of goes back to our philosophy that
if we can tap into the connections and
observe what's actually going across the
wire and what's on these streams, and
then we cross reference that with meta
from the system, whether that's process,
network, etc. that we're able to provide
a definitive story of truth regardless
of what your team has implemented. So
what are any standardized service that
you run or even services you get from
your cloud service provider which is a
vendor you can get a huge proliferation
of different
metrics learn quite a lot about how it's
running what are some metrics if you
have to implement it yourself what are
the metrics you should try to collect
from a your own usage of an external
service good question so I think. So,
let's pull these into a couple of
different categories. So, in the
category of performance, you're
primarily interested in latency and how
long does it take for your application
to get a a response back. And within
latency, you want to look at two aspects
of that. One is what's the impact of the
network as opposed to the time that it
takes for that particular vendor to
respond. And then then we move into the
uptime. And for uptime, it's important
to not just look at the network
availability, meaning a connection was
open, a connection was closed, but it's
really important to actually look at the
protocol level. For instance, HTTP has a
lot of protocol specific context that
you can't really get from the network
layer. And so diving into that is really
important for uptime. And then
bandwidth. So bandwidth is really
critical because there's so much cost
attribution to bandwidth especially your
cloud cost and so being able to
understand which vendors which
applications are consuming bandwidth
what's the size of these payloads and
just understanding that because you are
going to get a bandwidth bill and being
able to track that back to a vendor cost
is important for your inventory and your
financial accounting. You've mentioned a
couple of times the sensitivity of
different companies to the complete
failure or even a single failure of a
vendor API. Should companies
monitor failure rates and should they
page someone or file an alert if the
vendor is not performing adequately? I
think there's two parts of that. The
first part is the answer is definitely
yes. Regardless of which part we're
talking about here, yes, it's very, very
important. The way that our world gets
better is when customers hold vendors
accountable. And the more customers that
can be armed with real data that could
go back to a vendor and say, "Hey, we're
not getting the level of service that
we're paying for, the more likely that
that vendor is going to change." And
being armed with real data is the key.
That's that's one. But then I also think
that for teams, you kind of just have to
accept a certain level of this is what
it is. This is our vendor choice and
that's what we're using. Then we should
really know what we're working with. And
if it turns out that that vendor has a
consistent 3% error rate, then our
application should be able to handle
that and more to operate properly. We've
covered a lot of what can go wrong to
some extent, how to fix it. What about
fixing the process by which companies
adopt these vendors so they don't fix
the issues that you discover during your
audit and then a year from now they've
got a 100 new vendors they didn't know
about. What should the best practices
look like for adoption? Yeah, really
really got a strong opinion on this one.
I think what should happen is that you
should have a foundational monitoring
system set up so that you can run a
proof of concept or some sort of trial
and be able to have exactly the truth of
what happened. You should be able to see
the complete source of truth. This
vendor in the 48 hours, 72 hours, 90
days that we were running our test, we
can see that the P99 availability is
this. The P90 availability is this. And
that is just going to save your team a
lot of time front-loaded in
understanding the resilience, protecting
reputation, and just saving time
debugging these things. The biggest
mistake that I think we've heard over
and over is companies that assume a
level of excellence and they assume that
vendors all aspire to 59 uptime and only
to find out that that is a pipe dream.
What you're recommending then is measure
the vendor. You have some data and you
decide if you can live with the good or
bad. Absolutely. Yes. Measure and then
you have the reality. We've covered a
lot of the more general issues. I want
to ask about something I learned reading
about your product that you started out
as a proxybased design and that did not
work at to the level you wanted. So, you
switched to go with eBPF. Before I ask
the question, I'll mention we've done a
decent amount of coverage on eBPF on the
podcast in episode 619 most recently,
but there's several others. Can you tell
the story of why did the proxy design
not work out and what challenges or
issues did you run in going to ebpf? Oh,
yeah. So, I'll try to be brief on this.
This was a lot of fun, but essentially
with a proxy, there's a fundamental
problem. If you try to use a proxy to
solve the problems of clients connecting
to vendors in the same way that you
solve the problem of users connecting to
your services, it is a long and painful
road. And essentially the reason for
that is when your customers are
connecting to your services, you can
terminate SSL using your domain that
your TLS certificates that you own. You
can terminate and then you can do any
sort of monitoring and observability
that you want there. When you're
connecting to vendors, you do not own
that TLS certificate. The connections
are endto-end encrypted. The only way to
get in the middle of that is to do a
man-in-the-middle with a
self-signed Cert. When you introduce
that into your ecosystem, first and
foremost, you have security problems. If
that self-signed C gets in the wrong
hands, anybody who is on your network
can see everything that is going across
the wire. Now that you've introduced a
man in the middle, you have a single
point of failure. You have another bump
in the line. Any instrumentation that
you want to implement is now part of
that bump. And you add latency, you add
performance issues. So we found very
clearly when building our technology and
trying to take it to market that the
market said no, we're not going to do
that. And when we then looked at
recovering, how do we recover and how do
we really solve this problem? I early
early on in my career I worked in the
Linux kernel and the Solaris kernel and
particularly in virtual networking and
so I was really excited about what I was
hearing from EVPF. However, it had been
many years since I had worked in that
capacity. But I wanted to really dive in
and see what we could do in particular
to probe this into the Linux internals
where connections were being established
before encryption and after decryption.
And I was really interested in would it
be possible for us as these applications
are pushing their data through these SSL
read and SSL write functions, can we tap
into that and see the unencrypted data
before and the unencrypted data after?
And of course we have to be very careful
that we're always only operating in that
same host because you know that way the
data residency concerns you never want
to take data that was intended in one
location and now bring it over to
another and start to parse it. So we had
to do that on the machine inside the
Linux kernel where we didn't expose any
new boundaries. And I will say that the
only thing that was able to push our
team through our EBPF solution and all
of the challenges that presented were
that for as hard and challenging and
difficult as that was, it was equally
exhilarating and exciting and we could
do things that we just couldn't do
before. And it was so incredible to be
able to implement these low-level
solutions and just inject them right
into the kernel using ebpf. It was
extremely challenging to get up to speed
with how all of that worked. There are
so many different frameworks. BCC,
libpf, are we using C, are we using
Rust? Well, what about psylliums go, you
know, BPF and all of these different
tools and having to figure that out. It
was extremely challenging. extremely
even for a team that was very familiar
with kind of how kernel development
works and and Linux internals but now
kind of coming out on the other side I'm
extremely excited to help others get
into that and the ecosystem is starting
to bloom but there's so much that needs
to be done and and it's exciting. Can
you give one example of something you
can extract or see with EBPF that was
either really cool or surprising to you?
Yeah. So, this is something that we
ended up doing. One of the challenges
that we were facing is that we needed to
create a coherent string of a
connection. So this connection has this
source IP, this source port, this
destination IP, this destination port,
and then we've got to track that or
connect it up to the process that it
belongs to. And then we have got to
track that with all of the process
metadata. And so one of the things that
we ended up doing was as EVPF is still I
would say it's very much in its infancy
and there are not hooks for everything.
There's not hooks you can't hook into
every there's not well-defined hooks for
all the things that you need. So to
create a connection map and we needed
the underlying file descriptor to be
able to track that back to the process
that it belonged to and all that. What
we ended up doing is we ended up writing
hooks into kernel functions that would
receive pointers to memory locations
within the Linux kernel and we would
store that in a map and just hold on to
it and we would provide some sort of
lookup to it and then when a connection
was established we were able to take the
pointer location and map that with like
a file descriptor and I don't remember
exactly what we had in common to then go
and look that up out of the map. grab
that pointer location and then traverse
it in a completely different part of the
program. And what that ultimately did
was it just made it so possible for us
and to take whatever exists in the Linux
kernel, we can go get it. We just have
to know which function in the kernel has
a reference to that pointer and then
let's grab that pointer out. Let's store
it in a map and then later with all
these different events, we can pull it
back out and traverse that pointer. And
so that was one of the things that was
just really shocking. And here's the
specific example. So when we're trying
to tap into these SSL encrypted
connections, getting to before TLS,
after TLS, some of the applications use
OpenSSL, which makes it easier. But some
applications are built using Golang. And
Golang, as an example, is very, very
unique in the way that it builds. and it
bundles its own SSL library. And so we
were having a hard time mapping up the
connection that we were able to pull out
of a Go application with the actual
connection. And so we were able to use
that technique to actually find the
pointer and traverse it, get all the
information that we needed and then
present it up into our QTAP process that
had all the information that we needed.
I'm not sure I understood all of that,
but I'll make a attempt here in C. the
pointer points to something. So these
pointers point to kernel data structures
with all kinds of information and you
were able to map out where a bunch of
different things are and so that enabled
you to start from what you know and then
grab all the associated data from the
kernel that's useful. Yeah. So another
way to say that is with the way the ebpf
is written you have hooks and you can
hook into certain pieces of the system
whether that's a function call or system
calls or some sort of boundary and
you're given for the ebpf program that
you write you're given input that is
very specific to that hook and the
biggest challenge that we ran into was
when you don't have all the information
that you need in that hook. So
essentially the process that we
underwent was we were able to create
other programs to tap into other things
and take the pointers of things that we
needed and store them in maps so that
when the other programs would fire we
were able to get that information and
traverse those it was almost limitless
at that point once we got in that flow
what we could do. That's very cool.
We're pretty close to end of time.
Before we wrap up, would you like to
direct listeners anywhere on the
internet? Either you or point. So, I
don't have a great presence myself. I
know that's something that I have to
work on. But qoint is something that I'm
very passionate about. The team has
worked very hard. We're really excited.
So, I would say go check out
qoint.io. Qpo i n t.io.
We will put that in the show notes.
Tyler, thank you very much for speaking
to Software Engineering Radio today.
Thanks for having me and I really
appreciate it, Robert. It's great
talking. It's been a pleasure. And this
has been Robert Blumen for Software
Engineering Radio.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at
teamse-radio.net. This and all other
episodes of SE Radio is licensed under
Creative Common License
2.5. Thanks for listening.